<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exercise on Dripping Data</title>
    <link>/tags/exercise/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Exercise on Dripping Data</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/exercise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Fluid Management for Running</title>
      <link>/2018/06/23/fluid-management-for-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/23/fluid-management-for-running/</guid>
      <description>Update: 8/25/2018
I’ve been having a hard time with my long runs now that the weather is getting hot. I went on one in particular that was particularly tough. I was nauseous and felt hot afterwards for a long time. I probably had heat exhaustion. The next morning when I weighed myself I was about 5 lbs less than I thought I should be. This got me thinking that maybe I was also very dehydrated, even though I had taken water breaks at several water stops along the way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Treadmill Charts for Running Paces</title>
      <link>/2018/06/06/treadmill-charts-for-running-paces/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/06/treadmill-charts-for-running-paces/</guid>
      <description>I find it hard to pace myself on the road when doing interval workouts. The GPS apps aren’t good enough to maintain a steady pace at the goal so I always end up running too fast at the beginning then die at the end. I’ve found it easier to do these on the treadmill at the gym. The only problem is that it’s hard for me to convert between the paces I want to run and the miles per hour speed that are supplied by the treadmills.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runkeeper Data</title>
      <link>/2018/06/03/runkeeper-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/03/runkeeper-data/</guid>
      <description>Last summer I started running again after about 8 years off. I had run from my sophomore year of high school until the fall of 2008 when it seemed like I had a meniscus injury and I stopped running. I had run for 17 years, during which the longest break I had taken was maybe a few months. After I stopped, I always missed it, and when my son started training for a Scouting running achievement, I decided I would keep him company.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weight Training Data</title>
      <link>/2018/06/03/weight-training-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/03/weight-training-data/</guid>
      <description>I lifted weights regularly for two years but stopped recently because I decided to run more instead. I tracked my weight lifting using an app called Strong, and since it seemed that I had reached my peak of weight lifting I figured I would look back on my exercise over this time.
library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(ggplot2) library(lubridate) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;lubridate&amp;#39; ## The following object is masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## date dat &amp;lt;- read.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>