<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Dripping Data</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Dripping Data</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hawaii Coronavirus Update 2020-04-13</title>
      <link>/2020/04/13/hawaii-coronavirus-update-2020-04-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/04/13/hawaii-coronavirus-update-2020-04-13/</guid>
      <description>In my last post I used data from the New York Times Github repository. The authors update it within a day or two but I found a new crowdsourced data source from local tech community that is typically updated within minutes.
library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(ggplot2) library(lubridate) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;lubridate&amp;#39; ## The following object is masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## date library(scales) library(tidyr) library(zoo) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;zoo&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## as.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coronavirus in Hawaii</title>
      <link>/2020/04/04/coronavirus-in-hawaii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/04/04/coronavirus-in-hawaii/</guid>
      <description>Coronavirus is all anyone can think about these days, and the New York Times has become a repository for USA case data for some reason. They have been publishing the data on Github for now.
library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(ggplot2) library(scales) covid &amp;lt;- readr::read_csv(&amp;#39;https://raw.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Password Strength and Tidy Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2020/01/16/password-strength-and-tidy-tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/16/password-strength-and-tidy-tuesday/</guid>
      <description>I just found out about Tidy Tuesday, an educational exercise from the R for Data Science folks. The idea is that they publish a dataset every Tuesday for people to play around with. If you make something you’re proud of you can publish it on Twitter and use the hashtag #tidytuesday. I haven’t tried it before, but today’s one was a topic that was of interest to me–computer security and passwords.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Restarting with California Health Interview Survey</title>
      <link>/2020/01/13/restarting-with-california-health-interview-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/13/restarting-with-california-health-interview-survey/</guid>
      <description>Lately this blog has had a lot of descriptive posts about my life but not much that stretches my R abilities. Later this year my organization is holding its research day, so I decided to start practicing on a dataset that I last used about 7 years ago. The California Health Interview Survey is a survey of households that is weighted to be representative of the non-institutionalized population of California.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Much Water Garbanzo Beans Absorb in an Overnight Soak</title>
      <link>/2020/01/12/dry-garbanzo-bean-water-absorption/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/12/dry-garbanzo-bean-water-absorption/</guid>
      <description>I made a recipe for falafel today that involved soaking dry garbanzo beans/chickpeas. I happened to have weighed the dry garbanzo beans before soaking to see how much I had. Before soaking I had 403 g beans. After soaking in tap water at 77 degrees F the weight was 795 g. The beans gained 392 g of water or 97.3% of their dry weight. That’s close enough to call it double!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running Mileage in 2019</title>
      <link>/2020/01/05/running-mileage-in-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/05/running-mileage-in-2019/</guid>
      <description>After a great 2019 of running, I wanted to look back to see how far I had run. I regularly use a Garmin GPS watch to track my runs. The Garmin app and website let me look back at 12 months but after January 1, the 12 months was updated to February 2019 to January 2020 so I couldn’t see my 2019 totals anymore. I also sync to Strava but the Strava 2019 Year in Review mileage total (1216 miles) was off of the Garmin calculation that I saw at the end of December (~1300 miles).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prime Rib Temperature</title>
      <link>/2019/12/24/prime-rib-temperature/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/24/prime-rib-temperature/</guid>
      <description>We started a new family Christmas Eve tradition with roast prime rib. This year was a 6.61 lb bone on prime rib.
library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(ggplot2) dat &amp;lt;- tbl_df(read.csv(&amp;quot;../datasets/Prime_rib_temp.csv&amp;quot;)) I followed the Serious Eats recipe.
I cut off the bone then salted and let the bones and meat dry brine overnight.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iolani Football 1945-2019</title>
      <link>/2019/12/14/iolani-football-1945-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/14/iolani-football-1945-2019/</guid>
      <description>This week the local paper released a season recap of my alma mater’s football team. Included in the article was a link to game results dating back to 1945. It looked like there was an opportunity for a little data analysis on things like home and away records, records versus specific schools, etc. I downloaded the data and cleaned it for analysis in Google Sheets.
library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(lubridate) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;lubridate&amp;#39; ## The following object is masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## date library(ggplot2) iolani &amp;lt;- tbl_df(read.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turkey Data 2019 Update</title>
      <link>/2019/11/30/turkey-data-2019-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/30/turkey-data-2019-update/</guid>
      <description>Another Thanksgiving has come and gone and I have new data from this year’s 16 lb bird to add to the last time I updated this post.
An unexpected update problem was that the googlesheets package has been updated to googlesheets4 with new methods. I was able to figure out how to use the methods in blogdown and it opened a browser tab for me to authenticate. However it did so every time, so when I went to knit the actual HTML page, it hung, probably because I was not able to authenticate via the browser.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prime Ages</title>
      <link>/2019/11/29/prime-ages/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/29/prime-ages/</guid>
      <description>This past year our family members were 43, 43, 13, and 11 years old, which are all prime numbers. I wondered if there was or will be any other year where this will happen. There was probably a real math way to figure this out, but it was easier just to brute force calculate each year.
I took out the obvious years (where we are even ages), so starting when our daughter was born, I calculated how old each of us was or will be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross Country Results</title>
      <link>/2019/11/03/cross-country-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/03/cross-country-results/</guid>
      <description>The Hawaii high school cross country championship was held this weekend. At first, only the live time and place results were displayed, and there were no team scores calculated. That made me want to figure out how to get team scores out of the live results. Doing this also let me figure out some hypotheticals like what if the teams from division 1 and division 2 were combined in one race.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frog Bog Metrics</title>
      <link>/2019/04/22/frog-bog-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/22/frog-bog-metrics/</guid>
      <description>The school carnival was a couple weekends ago, and I volunteered at a game called Frog Bog. Players use a hammer to hit a lever that launches a frog at a rotating set of lily pads. You score by getting a frog in the lily pad. Players get four frogs per turn. I thought it might be nice to know the probability of success to help understand how to distribute prizes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fantasy Baseball Prediction Ensemble Model</title>
      <link>/2019/04/10/fantasy-baseball-prediction-ensemble-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/10/fantasy-baseball-prediction-ensemble-model/</guid>
      <description>It’s fantasy baseball season again, and it was time for my kids to do their draft with my friend’s kids. None of them know anything about baseball players except for the very top stars (Mookie Betts, Mike Trout), so they rely a lot on analyst predictions. Of course, one person’s predictions are not always that great, so inspired by Nate Silver, I set out to build a combination of several models to see if I could get a more accurate outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Mangrove Clearance on Water Quality at He&#39;eia Fishpond</title>
      <link>/2019/03/15/heeia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/15/heeia/</guid>
      <description>My daughter started doing a science project on the ecology of the Heeia fishpond. She collected a bunch of data, but since she’s only a 5th grader, I thought she might need some help with the analysis.
The premise is that the fishpond has been overgrown by invasive mangrove plants. The organization that runs the fishpond has been clearing back the mangroves. This helps to restore the water in the pond.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tenderfoot Paces</title>
      <link>/2019/02/16/tenderfoot-paces/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/16/tenderfoot-paces/</guid>
      <description>I had to organize the Tenderfoot scouts in my troop to learn some orienteering. The first step was to calculate how long their paces are. We went to the track and measured their pace count per 100 meters at least twice per scout. I wondered what the distribution looked like.
I used dplyr method to group and summarize the data. It’s a little overkill but it does make it super easy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Astronaut Fluid Shift Experiment</title>
      <link>/2018/08/25/astronaut-fluid-shift-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/08/25/astronaut-fluid-shift-experiment/</guid>
      <description>Today I ran an experiment with the students in my daughter’s First Lego League team. It was meant to demonstrate how fluid shifts in space. The kids measured their leg circumference at 3 different spots after standing for 10 minutes. They lay with their legs propped up in the air for 10 more minutes and then re-measured the circumference.
The inspiration for this activity came from the NASA website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Honolulu Traffic Tweets</title>
      <link>/2018/07/27/honolulu-traffic-tweets/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/07/27/honolulu-traffic-tweets/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fluid Management for Running</title>
      <link>/2018/06/23/fluid-management-for-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/23/fluid-management-for-running/</guid>
      <description>Update: 8/25/2018
I’ve been having a hard time with my long runs now that the weather is getting hot. I went on one in particular that was particularly tough. I was nauseous and felt hot afterwards for a long time. I probably had heat exhaustion. The next morning when I weighed myself I was about 5 lbs less than I thought I should be. This got me thinking that maybe I was also very dehydrated, even though I had taken water breaks at several water stops along the way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Treadmill Charts for Running Paces</title>
      <link>/2018/06/06/treadmill-charts-for-running-paces/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/06/treadmill-charts-for-running-paces/</guid>
      <description>I find it hard to pace myself on the road when doing interval workouts. The GPS apps aren’t good enough to maintain a steady pace at the goal so I always end up running too fast at the beginning then die at the end. I’ve found it easier to do these on the treadmill at the gym. The only problem is that it’s hard for me to convert between the paces I want to run and the miles per hour speed that are supplied by the treadmills.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runkeeper Data</title>
      <link>/2018/06/03/runkeeper-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/03/runkeeper-data/</guid>
      <description>Last summer I started running again after about 8 years off. I had run from my sophomore year of high school until the fall of 2008 when it seemed like I had a meniscus injury and I stopped running. I had run for 17 years, during which the longest break I had taken was maybe a few months. After I stopped, I always missed it, and when my son started training for a Scouting running achievement, I decided I would keep him company.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weight Training Data</title>
      <link>/2018/06/03/weight-training-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/03/weight-training-data/</guid>
      <description>I lifted weights regularly for two years but stopped recently because I decided to run more instead. I tracked my weight lifting using an app called Strong, and since it seemed that I had reached my peak of weight lifting I figured I would look back on my exercise over this time.
library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(ggplot2) library(lubridate) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;lubridate&amp;#39; ## The following object is masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## date dat &amp;lt;- read.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annual Leadership Forum Voting</title>
      <link>/2018/03/18/alf-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/18/alf-voting/</guid>
      <description>It’s been a while since I posted, but this weekend I returned to the American Academy of Pediatrics Annual Leadership Forum and I was able to cite my analysis on the top 10 resolutions.
In the spirit of looking further at the ALF data I decided to look at the voting records from this year. It seemed that most votes pass by at least 80% if not more. This includes the amendment votes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hawaii High School Football All-Stars</title>
      <link>/2017/12/20/hi-hs-football-allstars/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/20/hi-hs-football-allstars/</guid>
      <description>The local newspaper released a dataset of high school all stars from 1972 to 2017, and I thought it might be interesting to analyze the information. Some interesting questions were what schools have the most all stars, at what positions, and how this has changed over the years. I suspect that Saint Louis, Kahuku, and Waianae will be the top teams but who knows? Maybe there’s a secret dynasty that I never heard of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimated Prius Gas Mileage (December 2017 Update)</title>
      <link>/2017/12/19/estimated-prius-gas-mileage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/19/estimated-prius-gas-mileage/</guid>
      <description>(Updated to add googlesheets methodology and new data points)
I’ve seen some posts online suggesting that the miles per gallon estimates that your car provides are not accurate. I collected a few observations to see if this was true for my car.
Methods Each time I filled up the gas tank, I collected the number of gallons that were dispensed until the first automatic shutoff. I wrote down the estimated mpg, the trip odometer reading since the last fill-up, and the overall odometer reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fax Problem at Work</title>
      <link>/2017/12/15/fax-problem-at-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/15/fax-problem-at-work/</guid>
      <description>Our fax machine at work has been very slow lately. One of our frequently faxed numbers complained that it took over an hour to send a fax. Googling this problem didn’t result in any solutions, other than maybe learning that this is a common problem with fax over IP telephony. I decided to take a closer look at the logs.
The logs are printed out roughly every day or two.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turkey Data from 2017: A Bigger Bird</title>
      <link>/2017/12/04/turkey-temp-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/04/turkey-temp-2017/</guid>
      <description>Another Thanksgiving has gone by and another set of turkey roasting data is available.
This year’s turkey was quite a bit bigger than last year’s one (20 vs 14 lbs) because we usually roast one and buy another. The place we buy from wasn’t selling hot turkeys, so we decided to just make one big one. Other than the size, we used the same method as last year (see last year’s post).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VEX Scores and Google Sheets</title>
      <link>/2017/11/30/vex-scores/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/30/vex-scores/</guid>
      <description>My son is in a robotics competition this year. He has to score points by driving a robot around a course and making it pick up and place things. I thought it might be nice to chart his progress.
The real learning issue for today is using the googlesheets package to work with the data. I often enter data using this site and it would save me a lot of time to get the data directly from Google Sheets rather than downloading it as a csv.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimated Prius Gas Mileage</title>
      <link>/2017/10/21/estimated-prius-gas-mileage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/21/estimated-prius-gas-mileage/</guid>
      <description>I’ve seen some posts online suggesting that the miles per gallon estimates that your car provides are not accurate. I collected a few observations to see if this was true for my car.
Methods Each time I filled up the gas tank, I collected the number of gallons that were dispensed until the first automatic shutoff. I wrote down the estimated mpg, the trip odometer reading since the last fill-up, and the overall odometer reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publishing Hugo Page to UH Server</title>
      <link>/2017/09/09/blogdown_and_uh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/09/blogdown_and_uh/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been happy with Hugo to publish my blog, and I thought it would be cool to use it to revamp my personal webpage at the University of Hawaii. It turned out it wasn’t as easy as I thought it would be.
I created a new site using blogdown and the hugo_identity_theme.
new_site(theme = &amp;quot;aerohub/hugo-identity-theme&amp;quot;)) After playing around with the config.toml, I was ready to push the page to the university server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Birthday Problem Part 2</title>
      <link>/2017/08/09/birthday-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/09/birthday-part-2/</guid>
      <description>My family went on a cruise this month for 10 days, and in the dining room, it seemed that the waiters sang Happy Birthday to someone every night. The room was pretty full of people, but it struck me that some people might be lying to get the waiters to sing to them. This called for an analysis. What was the probability of a roomful of people having birthdays on each of 10 days in a row?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Disabled List Data from Major League Baseball</title>
      <link>/2017/07/17/dl-data-exploration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/17/dl-data-exploration/</guid>
      <description>I was interested in the duration of certain injuries for baseball players. It’s difficult to get data on this although I discovered a series of Google Sheets that documented disabled list (DL) stays over the years. I combined these sheets and cleaned these up manually. I entered these into R and crunched the data.
Methods I downloaded the data from Google and used the tidyverse tools to look at them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text Analysis of Security Now: tf-idf</title>
      <link>/2017/07/16/securitynow-text-analysis-tf-idf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/16/securitynow-text-analysis-tf-idf/</guid>
      <description>In the Security Now podcast, the hosts Steve Gibson and Leo Laporte often cite episodes that explain certain basic topics. They can never remember which episode covered a certain topic (e.g., how TLS works). As a follow-up to my previous post about text mining with the tidytext package, I decided to use see if I could make it easier to create an index for the series using term frequency and inverse document frequency analysis (tf-idf).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interisland vs. Overseas Electric Car Parking</title>
      <link>/2017/07/12/interisland-vs-overseas-electric-car/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/12/interisland-vs-overseas-electric-car/</guid>
      <description>The last time I went to the mainland I noticed that it seemed like there were a lot more electric cars parked in the overseas terminal parking lot than the interisland one. I wondered if it was a fluke or if there was a real difference. I collected some data to investigate!
Methods I had two trips back to back, my weekly interisland trip for work and my annual district meeting for my professional society.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Bookdown to create a Security Now Ebook</title>
      <link>/2017/07/10/securitynow-ebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/10/securitynow-ebook/</guid>
      <description>Recently I have been exploring the blogdown package to redo my website using Hugo, and it resurrected an old idea that I had. Security Now, one of my favorite podcasts, has transcriptions of each episode, and I thought it would be neat to put them into an e-book and read the old episodes that way. I tried using Calibre, but while it did work, I wasn’t able to figure out how to format it nicely.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AJ Mass’s Rule of Sevens</title>
      <link>/2017/07/03/rule-of-sevens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/03/rule-of-sevens/</guid>
      <description>On the baseball podcast I listen to, guest host AJ Mass proposed that a rule of thumb for a top 20 pitcher would be someone with an ERA &amp;lt; 3.5 and a K/BB ratio of &amp;gt; 3.5 (3.5 + 3.5 = 7). I wondered if this was actually the case (i.e., how many pitchers achieve this mark each season).
Methods I turned as usual to the Lahman database and the tidyverse packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Converting from Jekyll to Hugo</title>
      <link>/2017/07/02/hugo-conversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/02/hugo-conversion/</guid>
      <description>I’ve decided to convert this website from Github Pages/Jekyll to Hugo. Th inspiration for this came when I saw the website that Roger Peng put up for his live data analysis screencasts, and there was a big Hugo logo on the bottom. After learning more about this and discovering the blogdown package by Yihui Xie that is based on Hugo, I decided to take the leap in converting my Jekyll Github Pages site to Hugo (hosted on Github Pages).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text Analysis of Security Now</title>
      <link>/2017/07/01/securitynow-text-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/01/securitynow-text-analysis/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to try my hand at some text mining using the tidytext package, and I was wondering what I could look at. I love the podcast Security Now! by Steve Gibson and Leo Laporte, and I’ve always wondered if there was a way to build a good index of their podcast.
I used the tidyverse packages and tidytext by David Robinson. He and Julia Silge wrote the book from which most of these methods came from.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Justin Smoak and BABIP Trends</title>
      <link>/2017/06/26/justin-smoak-and-babip-trends/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/26/justin-smoak-and-babip-trends/</guid>
      <description>The podcast I listen to said something like, “I bet Justin Smoak must have one of the lowest BABIPs of anyone to this point in his career.” I thought it might be a good chance to explore this nebulous BABIP a little, what are the historical league and career trends in BABIP. Maybe 3 sentences are needed.
Or maybe a second paragraph. Or 2.
library(Lahman) library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(ggplot2) library(hrbrthemes) BABIP is calculated as balls in play (hits minus home runs) divided by total at bats that caused these balls in play (at bats minus strikeouts minus home runs plus sacrifice flies).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodreads Analysis</title>
      <link>/2017/06/19/goodreads-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/19/goodreads-analysis/</guid>
      <description>I just finished my 2017 Reading Challenge on Goodreads. My goal was to read 15 books this year. Poking around the site I discovered that I could export my data. I decided to have a look to see what my reading habits looked like, and since I was doing this for me, I decided to look at my wife’s data too.
Dataset library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(tidyr) library(ggplot2) library(lubridate) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;lubridate&amp;#39; ## The following object is masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## date library(hrbrthemes) books &amp;lt;- read.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Association between Years at a Private School and Academic Achievement</title>
      <link>/2017/05/30/years-at-private-school-and-academic-achievement/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/30/years-at-private-school-and-academic-achievement/</guid>
      <description>The kids brought home their yearbooks this past week, and it was time to settle a question that I have had for a long time. Do kids who enter their private school at kindergarten do better or worse than the kids who enter later?
Methods At this school there are two honor rolls (Headmaster’s List and Honor Roll). To get Headmaster’s List, a student must achieve a 3.5 grade point average with no grade below a B-.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>King Tides Citizen Science Project</title>
      <link>/2017/05/26/king-tides-gis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/26/king-tides-gis/</guid>
      <description>I read in the newspaper that the University of Hawaii was recruiting &amp;ldquo;citizen scientists&amp;rdquo; to help document the impact of this week&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;king tides&amp;rdquo; on our coastline. I uploaded some photos to the website but also found that we could download the dataset. I took this as an opportunity to learn something about geographic information systems (GIS) and R, and the end result was a pretty nice map of all the places that were photographed this week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pitchers with More Saves than Strikeouts</title>
      <link>/2017/05/21/saves-vs-strikeouts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/21/saves-vs-strikeouts/</guid>
      <description>On my favorite fantasy baseball podcast, the host mentioned the phenomenon of pitchers who had more saves than strikeouts. This seemed like it would be fairly uncommon since it seems that many closers are power pitchers (e.g., Aroldis Chapman). I decided to investigate further using the Lahman database.
Methods I used the Lahman database again, which is perfect for answering this kind of questions. It has a Pitching table that contains season long stats for every pitcher from 1871 to 2015 (as of this post).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Economical Iced Coffee</title>
      <link>/2017/05/11/iced-coffee/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/11/iced-coffee/</guid>
      <description>My wife and I like iced coffee but drinking it at Starbucks is expensive. I&amp;rsquo;ve been making it myself at home and it&amp;rsquo;s a reasonable facsimile at what I think is a much lower price. I decided to run the calculations to see how much we&amp;rsquo;re saving.
Grounds I tried a bunch of different coffees to see what would work the best: whole bean Kirkland (Costco) brand, whole bean Kona coffee, ground Lion coffee (a local brand), ground Folgers, and ground Kirkland.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bank Shot Win Analysis</title>
      <link>/2017/04/22/bank-shot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/22/bank-shot/</guid>
      <description>There’s a carnival game at the Iolani Fair called Bank Shot. You have to roll a ball on a ramp into a hole and win a prize. Get it in the green hole and you win tickets, and if you get it in the red hole, you win a big inflatable prize. I wondered what was the rate of hitting the red and green holes.
Here’s a picture of the game layout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AAP Annual Leadership Forum Consent Calendar Resolutions Less Likely to Make Top 10</title>
      <link>/2017/04/20/alf-consent-calendar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/20/alf-consent-calendar/</guid>
      <description>Last month I went to the American Academy of Pediatrics’ Annual Leadership Forum. This is a meeting of local chapter leaders from across the country where we make resolutions for the AAP to act on. Some resolutions were passed quickly as a group because they were not controversial. This process is called the “consent calendar”. The other resolutions were debated, sometimes at much length, before being voted on individually. At the end of the meeting we came up with the top 10 resolutions that we wanted the AAP to work on this year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Runs and Other Factors on Team Saves in Major League Baseball</title>
      <link>/2017/04/18/saves-and-runs-scored/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/18/saves-and-runs-scored/</guid>
      <description>From listening to my favorite fantasy baseball podcast it seems that there is a belief that teams that score lots of runs are not likely to produce saves. The idea seems to be that such teams would blow out their competitors and so have less opportunity for games to be saved. While it made sense, I wondered what the data said.
library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union library(ggplot2) library(Lahman) data(&amp;quot;Teams&amp;quot;) Teams &amp;lt;- tbl_df(Teams) Exploration of Saves over Time Saves did not become an official statistic until 1969 (source).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graphing Bean Sprout Respiration with the Hadleyverse</title>
      <link>/2017/04/09/bean-sprout-respiration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/09/bean-sprout-respiration/</guid>
      <description>My wife’s high school biology students did a lab recently and had difficulty graphing the pooled data. One student allegedly took 2 hours to figure out how to do this in Excel. This seemed like it would be a nice exercise to try in the Hadleyverse. To replicate this plot, I had to take her students’ data in wide form, tidy it up, calculate means for each group and time, and then plot these.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baseball Team Season Save Leaders with the Lowest Totals since 2000</title>
      <link>/2017/03/31/baseball-team-season-saves/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/31/baseball-team-season-saves/</guid>
      <description>I was listening to my fantasy baseball podcast last week, and the conversation turned to the Phillies closer situation. One host suggested that the Phillies might not have any pitcher with more than 10 saves this season. The other host thought that this would be unlikely. They looked quickly at the data and found that this has happened a few times since 2000. I wondered if there was a way to look this up using the Lahman database in R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pidgey Evolution: Effects on Combat Power and Hit Points (Updated)</title>
      <link>/2017/01/08/pidgey-evolution-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/08/pidgey-evolution-updated/</guid>
      <description>I was evolving some Pokemon in Pokemon Go and wondered how much the Pokemon’s attributes change after evolution. The attributes of interest were combat power (CP) and hit points (HP). I focused my analysis from Pidgeys because I had the most data points for this species.
I collected data from a couple of days’ evolution, available for viewing here. Both times I was using a Lucky Egg.
x &amp;lt;- read.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Birthday Problem at Work</title>
      <link>/2016/12/30/birthday-problem-at-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/12/30/birthday-problem-at-work/</guid>
      <description>My coworker keeps a list of our coworkers’ birthdays so she can plan a monthly celebration. There are 36 of us in the office, and it turns out that none of us have the same birthday. My coworker wondered what was the chance of that happening.
As it turns out, the birthday problem is a classic probability question. Given a certain number of people, what is the probability that two of them have the same birthday?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electric Vehicle Parking at Honolulu International Airport</title>
      <link>/2016/12/29/electric-vehicle-parking-at-hnl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/12/29/electric-vehicle-parking-at-hnl/</guid>
      <description>In Hawaii, electric cars park for free at state owned parking lots. This is a big benefit when we travel since the airport parking lot is normally $18 per day. I wondered how much money the state loses on the electric car parking at the airport. Because I travel to Maui every week for work, I was able to collect some data to try to answer this question.
Methods I made video recordings of parked cars while driving through the Honolulu International Airport interisland parking structure between November 29, 2016 and December 28, 2016.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pidgey Evolution: Effects on Combat Power and Hit Points</title>
      <link>/2016/12/14/pidgey-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/12/14/pidgey-evolution/</guid>
      <description>I was evolving some Pokemon in Pokemon Go today and wondered how much the Pokemon’s attributes change after evolution. The attributes of interest were combat power (CP) and hit points (HP). I focused my analysis from Pidgeys because I had the most data points for this species.
I collected data from one day’s evolution, available for viewing here.
x &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;../datasets/evolution.csv&amp;quot;) x &amp;lt;- tbl_df(x) pidgeys &amp;lt;- filter(x, pokemon == &amp;quot;Pidgey&amp;quot;) pidgeys ## # A tibble: 12 × 7 ## pokemon CP_pre HP_pre kg_pre CP_post HP_post kg_post ## &amp;lt;fctr&amp;gt; &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; ## 1 Pidgey 270 NA NA 533 NA NA ## 2 Pidgey 267 NA NA 515 NA NA ## 3 Pidgey 259 NA NA 526 NA NA ## 4 Pidgey 212 NA NA 413 NA NA ## 5 Pidgey 209 43 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Secret Santa Picker</title>
      <link>/2016/12/09/simple-secret-santa-picker/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/12/09/simple-secret-santa-picker/</guid>
      <description>A post about automating Secret Santa assignments popped up in my Facebook feed the other day. This being the Christmas season, I took a look. It seemed a bit complex, and I wondered if I could make it more efficient.
The original function took in a list of people (e.g., Ann, Bill, Chris). Using a nested while-for loop, it randomly picked a name (Bill), and matched it to the first person in the list (Ann:Bill).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Unlucky Fantasy Football Season Is Over</title>
      <link>/2016/11/30/unlucky-fantasy-football/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/30/unlucky-fantasy-football/</guid>
      <description>The regular fantasy football season just finished, and as usual, my team underperformed. I had the 3rd most points in the league and finished 7 out of 8 teams with a record of 4-8. I wondered what were the chances of such a bad record. This called for a simulation!
Methods I transcribed all the scores for each game into a spreadsheet and loaded it into R.
library(dplyr) ## ## Attaching package: &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39; ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:stats&amp;#39;: ## ## filter, lag ## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:base&amp;#39;: ## ## intersect, setdiff, setequal, union dat &amp;lt;- read.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convection vs. Conventional Electric Oven Speed in Roasting Turkey</title>
      <link>/2016/11/25/turkey-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/25/turkey-graph/</guid>
      <description>It’s the day after Thanksgiving, and we have data on another turkey. This year our electricity went out just before I was going to put the turkey in our old electric oven so I had to go to my parents’ house to cook the turkey. They just got a fancy new oven with convection roasting, and they claimed it would be faster. This called for an analysis!
Methods Like last year, I took measurements of the probe thermomenter inserted into the deepest part of the breast.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will I Pass My Board Exam?</title>
      <link>/2016/11/15/pass-my-board-exam/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/15/pass-my-board-exam/</guid>
      <description>I am in the process of studying for my pediatrics board recertification and the pass rate is rumored to be about 75% of the questions correct. I got 163/199 (82%) of the questions correct on my practice exam. What is the probability that I will get at least 75% on my 200 question board exam based on this performance?
Here’s the exact binomial way to figure it out.
The idea is that if my probability of getting any question right is 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scale Model of Solar System</title>
      <link>/2016/11/06/scale-model-of-solar-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/06/scale-model-of-solar-system/</guid>
      <description>One of my son’s Cub Scout “adventures” requires him to create a scale model of the solar system. We sketched the calculations on the back of a receipt over lunch. We started with the distance we figured that we would use (length of our street, 387 feet) and then calculated the distances to each planet based on this. I figured it would be neat to create a function in R that would return a table of the relative distances based on a given model solar system radius.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Most Yards of Offense by a College Football Team in a Shutout Loss</title>
      <link>/2016/10/03/football-shutouts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/10/03/football-shutouts/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The purpose of this document is to explore the most yards in a shutout loss for a college football team. It was inspired after the University of Hawai`i gave up 462 yards in shutting out San Jose State on November 15, 2014. I wanted to see if I could use the dplyr package to explore this question.
library(dplyr) ## Warning: Installed Rcpp (0.12.12) different from Rcpp used to build dplyr (0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gas vs. Electric Car Operating Prices in Honolulu</title>
      <link>/2016/09/11/electric-car-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/09/11/electric-car-economy/</guid>
      <description>Our family has an electric car (Nissan Leaf) and a hybrid (Toyota Prius), and we often have to choose which one we will take out on the weekend. I wondered which one was cheaper to operate and which one was better for the environment.
Wallet Impact The Leaf travels about 4.8 miles per kilowatt hour (kwh), and the Prius gets about 55 miles per gallon (mpg). Our electricity costs about $0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Late Can My Patient Be</title>
      <link>/2016/08/14/late-patients/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/14/late-patients/</guid>
      <description>When a patient doesn’t come to their developmental behavioral pediatrics appointment, it’s bad for my employer, but it’s an unexpected boon for me. Most of my patients seem to come early and only a few arrive later than 5-10 minutes past their appointment time. I wanted to know when I could start to give up on them and start doing something else. When would it be likely that a patient will no-show?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work for Dinosaur Speed Geocache</title>
      <link>/2016/08/05/dinousaur-speed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/05/dinousaur-speed/</guid>
      <description>This is the work for the geocache we did today. The geocache description instructed us to measure the stride length and footprint length of some dinosaur tracks at the Dinosaur Ridge hike outside of Denver, Colorado. The kids and I looked at both the thinner Ornithomimus tracks and the thicker Iguanodontid tracks. Here’s the work, done in R:
First, set up a table of the data. The units for stride length and footprint length are meters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Flashcard Deck Size Using Linear Regression</title>
      <link>/2016/07/22/flashcard-deck-size-prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/07/22/flashcard-deck-size-prediction/</guid>
      <description>I’m studying for my pediatric recertification board exam right now, and to help me remember things, I’m making flashcards as I read an exam study book. Lately, I’ve been wondering how many flashcards I will have by the time I reach the end of the book.
I average about 15 pages a day and about 45 flashcards a day, or 3 flashcards per day. The book itself is 849 pages long, with the real content starting on page 43.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reverse-In Parking in Hawaii and California</title>
      <link>/2016/07/14/reverse-parking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/07/14/reverse-parking/</guid>
      <description>Introduction One of my mainland-born friends is annoyed that Hawaii drivers like to reverse their cars into parking stalls much more than the mainland. My wife, who is also from the mainland, agreed with him enthusiastically. Whether this is appropriate parking behavior or not, I had never noticed it before, so I figured it was something I could test with some observations. I had a trip coming up to the mainland, and I was able to collect some data to test whether the Hawaii drivers were really so different than their California counterparts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting photo directories with R and exiftool</title>
      <link>/2016/06/13/sorting-photo-directories-with-r-and-exiftool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/06/13/sorting-photo-directories-with-r-and-exiftool/</guid>
      <description>We were fans of Google&amp;rsquo;s Picasa photo organization software, but when it was discontinued, I decided that I would like to transfer all my digital photos onto an external drive and then into Adobe Lightroom. To do so, however, my &amp;ldquo;research&amp;rdquo; told me that it would be best to group them into catalogs based on year, mainly because I have on the order of 10^5 photos.
I had my pictures organized into about 300-400 directories by event.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rolling 3 Doubles in Monopoly</title>
      <link>/2016/05/30/monopoly-simulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/05/30/monopoly-simulations/</guid>
      <description>Tonight my two kids and I were playing Monopoly. It’s a terrible, brutal game that usually ends in bad feelings, but for some reason they always want to play it. One of the rules of the game is that if you roll a double (e.g., two 2s), you get another turn. However, if you roll doubles three times in a row, you are sent to jail.
I wondered what was the probability of rolling 3 doubles in a row.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Up and running!</title>
      <link>/2016/05/29/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/05/29/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>This is the start of a new blog for me. I mostly completed the Data Science specialization on Coursera and I use some of these skills in work, but still I am just an amateur at this. I hope to use this site as a sort of notebook to document some of my thoughts and keep my already waning programming skills up. Without peer review, I can&amp;rsquo;t vouch for the accuracy of anything I say here, so please don&amp;rsquo;t take anything I write here too seriously!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>